Hello,
somebody. Before we start today's episode, I want to personally invite you to an Ask Me Anything over on Patreon. All you need to do is go over to patreon.com forward slash Hello, Somebody and become a member. And on September 24th, you can join me.
Ask me questions about anything you want. Go ahead.
And hop over there right now,
patreon.com/hellosomebody.
Now, today's
episode is so good, I sat down with Famous the Rapper. He's a proud father, an independent artist, and there's a big surprise in this one. So here
we go.
So,
Famous, it's wonderful for you to be able to join us today. Your hip-hop name is Famous, but your birth name is Robin Lee Dorsey Jr. Yes, I'm a
junior. You
are a junior. I got a junior, too. Famous
actually means Robin, the definition of it. Is
that right? Yes,
if you look it up. Famous means Robin.
Famous means Robin. So you didn't just pull this name out because it was hip and cool. It has...
deep meaning
it has deeper meaning to it yeah that's a beautiful thing so you were born in queens new york yes jamaica queens new york jamaica
queens new york are you still in new york
yes i'm in
new york i reside in queensbridge right now
and what is it about you and this vocation this gift that god has given you why rap why hip-hop
I
was into sports at first. The first sport I ever played was baseball. I used to live in Puerto Rico. Oh, wow. Yes, I lived in a few places other than New York,
like Puerto
Rico, Connecticut, Virginia, Washington, D.C., and Florida.
And you picked up your love for baseball in Puerto Rico?
Yeah, I started off with baseball. My favorite sport is football, though. Okay. Football and basketball. I'm very talented at that, too.
Well you multi-talented,
got many talents. Hip hop is my passion,
like I
have a
real passion for that.
And when did you know that this was your thing? You know, so often it's hard for people to find that thing that gives them life, that breathes life into them, that they would do even if they made no money ever. It's just their calling. When did you know that rap, hip hop, when did you know that was your calling?
Late teenage years, because before I used to play with it and recite other people's lyrics and
then change up the song, change up their song, put my own lyrics. I used to do it just for fun, like rap in the lunchroom in school and stuff like that. People used to tell me that you should take it serious because you're talented at it. At first, I didn't look at it like that because I was more focused on sports. But yeah, I have a passion for it. It's not about the money, it's not about that. I do it for the passion first.
-
Passion first, money
second,
totally. - I feel a lot of people now, they don't take time to put the creativity into their craft.
Like they
don't put, like I put a lot of effort into it. Like I read books to put in my rhymes, everything. Read dictionaries
to find new words to
put in.
It's very clear that you put a lot of effort into this vocation, this gift of yours, which leads me to something
else that it is important that even though people are gifted, you got to put some effort towards the gift. And that's really what you're saying.
And I try to make my music relatable too. I want people to actually feel the music. I feel like that's...
missing right now.
Well, music is
the
universal language, they say. So you know what? You're bringing up for me two of my favorite songs by you. Obviously, I came to get
to know your gift through
Somebody who's close to me, my brother.
Yes, I spoke to him. I actually spoke to him yesterday. You did. Yeah, we keep in contact often. Very good brother, very good brother. Yes, he is. Yeah, we talk. I appreciate him. I tell him every day I appreciate him. Every
morning we talk and he told me every morning his wife has to wake up to your music because he's waking up to your music. He
told me the same thing
yesterday. So
two songs that I really enjoy for myself.
"Daddy's Little Girls."
- Yeah. - I see a lot of me inside the actions. Inside I'm asking how I can keep 'em away from life distractions. So they can go in situations knowing the right reaction. - And "Drunk With Jesus."
- I just feel
like I'm chosen. I'm
chosen. -
Okay.
- So I want to start with "Daddy's Little
Girls," a tribute to your three daughters?
- Yes, three daughters.
Zyviana, Avani, and Lana.
I could feel, not just through the words
you were saying, "All I have in this cold world is me and my girl." All I have in this cold world is me and my girl. It's just me and my girl. Obviously, your baby girl inspired the song.
That's also the reason why I do music for them. I want to provide them a better life.
How
did you set out to start to think of putting the words of that song together? They
were
your inspiration, but you were very clear about the world is cold and
how you wanted them to. And I'm paraphrasing. I'm giving you my interpretation of the song and you tell me you wrote it. You're the creator. But my interpretation was this was a song to instill and reinforce for your baby girls that you as their father, they really are your first loves.
You love them. They are a creation. They are a gift to you. That they are beautiful and the world is going to see them that way. You even put in some remarks about how, you know, the boys got to beat them back basically. That their worth, you wanted them to know their intrinsic worth outside of another man or woman loving them. That number one, you love them. That's first and foremost. And you wanted them to know their value and you saw them as a gift.
That's how I interpreted the song.
It
is like that. And I want them to know that they love-- I tell my daughter that they're beautiful every day and I love them. I make sure I say that every time I see
them, I tell them I love them, Daddy loves you. I want them to know their worth, too, that love come from within, not
outside. So
I want them to know their worth in this world also, as long as they have parents that love them. But the words just flowed out. The words is already in me because of the love for my daughters. So it's already-- it was easy to make
that song.
You also talk about how you want to give them the world and that they also kind of change.
The views about
women
was
inspired by them.
Yes, yes. Because before I used to have many women in my life, like irresponsibly. Like the man I used to be, I wouldn't want my daughters to be with that. Now that I'm grown, I've grown a lot now that I have daughters.
Evolution is a beautiful thing and to be able to have that kind of self-reflection is beautiful too.
Yeah, and I'm going to be an example but because I'm the first person, I'm the first man they love. So, I want to be that example for them.
Amen. To see what a man is supposed to
be like.
Yeah, you took the words right out of my mouth. You are the first man that they love and so they will reflect and also their value comes from knowing that love from
you.
just
a beautiful song i certainly encourage anybody whether it's a mother or father but if you have daughters to really play this song that famous created it's a love song to your
daughters it
really yes it is and i feel like like the world needs that today too because a lot of fathers missing out there in their child's life and i think that's the biggest like one of the biggest problems in like the urban community too it's like single motherhood and i think that's the plague in the black community
Women do take a lot upon themselves. Black women, I believe, and I need to go back and double check this stat, but
I think it's 75% of black households or so are led by single mothers.
Now, it is very sad. Now, being a single mother or being the custodial parent doesn't necessarily mean that the father
is not engaged in some way, but the burden of being that custodial parent is so heavy on black women.
It
could be mentally draining on a woman, too. Oh, yeah. And it has a very bad effect on a child growing up.
Yes, I agree. We need
more fathers back in the home. They're being misguided by other things, by media, by music, by just other things. And
they got a
lot of impressionable minds, too.
They
try to do stuff to fit in with the wrong crowd, just to look cool
or... - Definitely need that kind of guidance and black women need relief. So it would be good. You know,
there are a lot of surrogate dads, you know, out at uncles, people who children may not necessarily be their biological children. They pour into those kids,
whether it's a teacher or a coach or someone from a church or a mosque. So I thank God. I just want to give a shout out to the fathers out there. Black fathers get a bad rap all the
time.
yes i
want to shout out the good ones because there are some good ones and there are some black men who have stepped up to help uh commute their own their
community yes that's good it's a good thing we need
that it's a beautiful thing now leads me to my next song drunk with jesus
i dress quick headed to the local spot to sip something i get there sit slumped in the chair i started with shots but cardi on rocks dizzy everything around me just stops i'm bugging out That's how I see the original song.
I'm
drunk by myself, and he can drive in the car, just using the drunken stage or whatever. So I wanted to flip that and make my own type of song, original from that. And I've decided to make Drunk With Jesus.
It's just
basically, the song is me being
drunk with Jesus, me having a conversation with Jesus. But basically, the stuff that we're
taught in the Bible and stuff.
how
the world is today, how it's totally opposite of that. Like, I feel like the world today is more corrupted than ever. It's like Sodom and Gomorrah, it's like Bob along right now. Can things change? Like, how can I play my part, you know, to make change in the world? I try to do my part through
music. And that
is a gift. In that song, when Jesus is talking to you, I mean, you're having this conversation about frustration and about what's happening in the world and the whole
notion
of
you
know, has nature run its course? You know, is this it? You know,
why is
all these bad things happening in the world? And pretty much Jesus is saying this stuff has to happen, has to run its course until I return. You know, I'm like, yes! 'Cause I'm a church girl. So, you know, this song spoke to me on many levels. So pretty much the chaos and the pain, the ups and the downs and the turnarounds, like all of these things
or,
the
yin and the yang, all of these things are necessary to happen for his
return.
I'm
just looking for answers. That's basically it. I'm looking for answers and how can I do my part?
Yeah. I wish more of us asked how we could do our part. And then stay on your purpose. In that song, it was not get caught up in everything that's happening around you so much so that you're knocked off your purpose.
Yes, I think that everybody needs to focus on their purpose. I think that's the main thing people need to focus on what their purpose in life
is. And
to know what it is, first you got to understand what it is. Yes, you got to
understand that, yes. You got to understand yourself. That's why you got to learn yourself. A lot of people don't know who they
are.
True that.
I
really I really truly enjoyed that that song I must have I've listened to that song at least 10 times so hopefully
that's one of my favorites
actually good by the time we talk again I might have it memorized yeah
I really like that song yeah I
think it's I think
it's creative it is it's deep people can relate yeah one of their
religious or not, I believe that there's a lot for everybody in both of the two songs that I really like. And I know that you have so many others, but I wanted
to pick my favorite.
And
when I do my music, I try not to be like too preachy. I try to still keep the entertainment value
in it. Yeah. I don't want to come off too preachy 'cause I could, but I don't want to do that 'cause it won't be entertaining. Duke's probably boring. So I try to throw little bits and
pieces of wisdom
into it and drop jewels on it and you can get you know what you take out of it
now who who influences you besides your daughters who are the other influencers in your life
as far as
the music goes my my biggest influence was naz naz and jay-z they're probably
my biggest influence i like the storytelling from them
and i
can relate
to them because we come from the same parts the
expression of african americans and our ancestors i mean hip-hop is an amalgamason of all of that the blues -
With the Jansen, yeah.
- Yeah, all of them.
at right it's not just the rap and it's DJing it is dancing it's graffiti yeah
it's all of it educators it's like it's a cultural movement but it is very much rooted in our experience in America pre the name of hip-hop I mean I can see it in the dance and the way we express ourselves throughout history
and even
going back to the continent itself
So
we go old school in the 70s and the 80s, you know, Sugarhill Gang comes to mind. Rapper's Delight. But I'm also thinking about one of my favorite songs, totally dating myself, but the double Dutch bus rolling down the
street.
You know, those kinds of things where it had these messages. It was fun. It was teaching, as you laid out. Not too preachy, but it also had lessons and messages. So we got our old school. And then I guess we would call the next phase of the '80s, like the mid '80s into the '90s. Some experts say that that is the new school hip-hop, where you got Run-D.M.C.
and L.L.G., Raquel, Big Daddy Kane, Salt-N-Pepa.
Coogee rap, yes, public enemy, fight the power. It was very
diverse, like late 80s, 90s. MC light, you know. Yes, MC light, Queen Latifah.
Queen
Latifah, yes. When I listen to those kinds of songs, it's very clear what the messaging is. Now when we come up into the
21st century, it's kind of hard to see the messaging anymore. Terrible. What are your
thoughts about that? There is no message.
Today's hip-hop is terrible.
There's some. There's people like J. Cole, Kendrick, that still stick to the true, like the art form, but for the most part, music is terrible. There's no message, and I feel like everybody feel they can do it now. That's why. It's been so big that everybody wants to do it, and a lot of people can't, but they feel they can infiltrate it because they see so many people, like untalented people doing it, and they say, oh, well, I can do this too, so they use it more as a hustle instead of a passion.
So, I think that's terrible. I think you should do it because you love to do it. Like anything you do, you should love to do it. You put your all into it. You shouldn't do it just for a means to make money or hustle. That's like the definition of a cultural vulture.
Do you think that culturally that rap could ever move back to that?
to the
foundation or is it too commercialized? I think it could, but it's a problem because a lot of the people that we grew up listening to
are backing up the trash music. That's the problem right there. They don't back up people that's true to hip hop, but I think they do it from a business standpoint, I guess.
because i think that's what the younger people want to listen to now but for me my message is i just want people to relate to the music and i try to bring it bring it back to what it used to be well you
know i'm going to continue to hold our hope with you that hopefully we can that's
what i'm trying to do
go backwards to go forward yes i
would love to put on people more like me but i see some people
coming
Like Griselda, you ever heard of it? No. Griselda,
you kind of stick to the roots. They sound more like a Wu-Tang. Oh, I love the Wu-Tang. Yeah, Wu-Tang. There's like little
bits and pieces coming back. I think it's slowly
coming back. So you're not out there alone in trying to keep alive that old school vibe. Yeah. The roots and origins of hip-hop.
I
wouldn't say old school. People tell me that. They hear my music just because I can rap. They call me old school. I feel it's more timeless than old school.
-
Okay, well, let's go on and use toddler, but you know old school is...
Yeah, I know, I know, Judy, I know what the name is. -
That means deep. - Yeah. - Not superficial, deep. - Yeah, no, vintage, classic. - Vintage, okay, we're gonna say vintage school.
-
And what made you wanna do the podcast?
You went from Bernie Sanders to hip-hop. Well, you know,
I had a podcast before called "We The People," and I've been a news commentator. So I've always tried to be engaged in things that would allow me to give voice to people's hopes and their dreams. And so podcasting is just another way to do it.
Absolutely. When I was on the campaign, had no time for this kind of stuff. I mean, that's when the whole hello, somebody was born. I was just inspired as I was giving my speech and I was looking out into the crowd. And I saw their passion because it was right after Senator Sanders had a heart attack. And this was our first rally after the heart attack. So everybody was just full of hope and really happy that he recovered. And because I come from, you know, call and response is a big deal in the art form.
and I wanted people to feel what I was saying
and I
wanted them to respond. I wanted them to let me know. So since I didn't know everybody's name out there, I was just inspired to say, "Hello, somebody." And so the crowd just started saying, "Hello, somebody." My love for hip hop, I'm an advantage of people like Tupac,
definitely i mean absolutely love love love tupac i mean famous when i was on the floor of the senate as a state senator i would quote tupac on the florida senate my colleagues looking at me like i was crazy oh yeah we're gonna bring some urban poetry to the floor of the ohio senate got money for wars but can't feed the poor hello somebody yes
I
mean, that was my thing. And I put him, you know, just as people always quote the founding fathers or the framers or this famous person or that famous person. A lot of times in our hip hop and our urban culture, people don't necessarily think that it is worthy of being quoted. They marveled at the fact that I was quoting Thomas Jefferson and Tupac Secure. You damn right. I did. It's relatable because when you do that, you
can relate to the youth.
That's it. I mean, it's a universal money
for wars, but can't feed the poor. People can relate to that young and old, especially if you are poor and suffering. And so LL Cool J is my absolute favorite. You
and your own brother, your brother said the same
thing. Yes, yes. And maybe we kind of rubbed off on each other, but I have a whole playlist of LL Cool J for my workout. So when I'm running the treadmill or jumping rope or boxing on my boxing bag, as I visualize people who work my last damn nerves,
i'm listening to i'm listening who's one of
the greatest one of the greatest
to ll and then as far as you know for deeper consciousness certainly his public enemy the tupac type killer mike michael render and i have become really good friends and i listen to him a lot too and he goes deep so i listen to him on his activist side you know his artist side as well but the run dmcs of the world
you know biggie mace yeah yeah those are not so much because
he's
he
talks about some of these issues
too. - Yeah, yeah, he really does. And you're right, like the people, Kendrick Lamar and some of the others are picking up on some of that
tradition. And it's a beautiful thing to see. I'm not a, I love a good beat, but I think you and I may have in common, words matter.
and
so i need some substance the
most important thing they are i don't you need substance for your soul i mean it just can't be about that's what's missing today about the substance there's no content yeah let's get some substance for our soul let's
get substance for our soul and so that's why when i pick my beats i want the beast that feeling to it come on
i don't want the beast to just because most of the beast now is just it all sound the same no originality to it
now
I mean, people need to make money. There's nothing wrong with that, especially if nobody gets hurt. I
don't believe that people should make money off of other people's misery. You know what? Music is a lesson. It's not only
its own language, but it teaches many lessons. - I think if they played more
conscious music, I
think more people would be conscious. - I agree with you. - 'Cause they play the same songs over and over. They get it stuck in your head. I feel like it brainwashes
the
youth. - The best is yet to come for
you, sir.
Thank you. I really appreciate it.
You are so welcome. It's an
honor to be on your podcast. All right, babies, you take good care, darling. All right, you too.
It was so great having that dialogue with Famous. And you know what?
He did
something spectacular for Hello Somebody. Oh, my God.
And I got
to give a shout out to my brother because it was his idea. Don't tell him. Don't tell him I gave him a shout out.
to
my little brother, who's bigger and taller than I am. But I am the oldest, baby. But yes, my brother had this idea and Famous
came through. So I want you to listen intently to the Hello Somebody theme song, baby. This song,
this rap, this art.
Baby,
we'll make you move and groove. Take a listen.
I believe it. I
believe that the leader of this in the
universe has
given us two hands. One
to reach
one to reach one to the city
as we climb, we
climb. Yeah,
change is coming. The pain is numbing. Try to shoot for the stars if you're going to aim for something. Embrace the love for your brother and sister. Unity's the mission brush. We need to puzzle this picture. Let's paint it up. Frame it up for the world to see. Hang the hatred up. Enough is enough is enough. Making changes
And Turner, her voice is the truth, her wise words inspire the youth to keep their eyes on the roof. It's the end, never give up, keep conquering goals, to the I, intelligence, silver, wisdom is gold. Back to the end, now is your time, stay firm, don't fold, to the A, all you need is the three bones, that's what Granny said. Now I'ma make sure these words from Granny spread, for all of here, just give her your ear. She can take you to the promised land, I swear, world peace is what they fear. From Queens to Cleveland, Ohio, we here.
Famous.
We will not be neutral.